Guide to the Special Collections Research Center oral history collection, 1972-2016 MS0371
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Rosemary Hills school integration oral history and documentation project, 1972-1977; Series 1; 14 Linear Feet 7 full and 2 partial record center cartons, 1 document box, and 2 cassette tape boxes
  - Case study on school desegregation in Montgomery County, Maryland, around 1972-1977; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 record center carton (Box 12)
  - Publications about school desegregation on a national level, around 1972-1977; 3 Linear Feet 2 record center cartons (Box 13, Box 14)
  - Newspaper clippings about school desegregation, around 1972-1977 (Box 15)
  - Administrative files for grant received from Maryland Committee for the Humanities and Public Policy on school desegregation, around 1972-1977 (Box 15)
- George Washington University oral histories, 1974-; Series 2; 7.75 Linear Feet 7 full and 1 partial document boxes, 1 slim document box, 2 partial records center cartons, 4 partial tape boxes, and numerous digital recordings and transcription files
  This series consists of oral history interviews related to the George Washington University conducted since 1974. Interviewees include university presidents, faculty, staff, administrators, and alumni.
  Interviews were first conducted as part of the Oral History Program started by Mary Jo Deering in the 1970s. These include a series of eighteen interviews with Elmer Louis Kayser between 1975 and 1977. Kayser was University Historian at that time and was affiliated with the University as a student and faculty member from 1914 to his death in 1985.
  In 1987, immediately prior to his retirement, GW President Lloyd Elliot gave a lengthy and broad-ranging series of oral history interviews that are included in this series. This series also includes a similar set of interviews conducted with President Stephen Joel Trachtenberg and his wife Francine Zorn Trachtenberg at the time of his retirement, however, the Trachtenbergs' interviews are not yet open to researchers.
  In 1988, University Archivist G. David Anderson renewed efforts to document GW history through oral histories with faculty, staff and alumni. Other oral histories have also been conducted over the years by staff of Special Collections and by GW students. Under the direction of University Archivist Bergis Jules in 2013-2014, oral histories that expanded and diversified the picture of GW's history were pursued.
  A separate series of oral histories conducted by the Medical Center Oral History Committee in the 1980s focused on faculty, staff, and alumni of that GW division. However, oral histories conducted with some of the same individuals by members of the library's oral history program also exist in this series.
  The series is intellectually arranged alphabetically by interviewee last name, and chronologically thereunder when multiple interviews exist with the same person.
  Physically, the materials for a single interview (e.g., cassette tapes, reel-to-reel tape, and transcript) are spread across multiple boxes because they are stored according to format. Transcripts and files for interviews that are currently closed have been moved to boxes whose numbers begin with an "R", although the recordings continue to be stored alongside those for open interviews.
  Some interviews in this series are closed due to a lack of signed releases from the interviewees (many releases from the Anderson era, in particular, could not be located). These restrictions are noted at the item-level.
  - John G. Allee interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 July 18; 2 Cassettes (Box 5, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of release signed by Allee.
  - Don Balfour interviewed by David Anderson, 1995 April 7; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 5, Cassette 3)
  - Armecia J. Banks interviewed by Tasha Dorsey, 2014 April 11; 1 digital object(s)
    Biographical and Historical
    Armecia J. Banks was born October 9, 1954 in Washington, DC to Mable Banks. She has one son, Rodney I. Riley, Jr., of Washington, DC. Her first job was with Mackey Co. Ms. Banks received a high school degree at age 50, and began her career at GW in 1973 working in the dish room in Thurston Hall. She has worked at various food service locations, including Subway, Quiznos, and Starbucks. She is a member of Free Gospel Deliverance Temple, where she sings in the choir and serves as a greeter and member of the outreach team.
    This oral history was conducted on April 11, 2014 by graduate student Tasha Dorsey. Ms. Dorsey conducted the oral history as part of a University Archives Diversity Research Fellowship awarded for the 2013-14 academic year.
    The oral history discusses Armecia J. Bank's career working at GW in food services and her life experiences.
  - David McGuire Bates interviewed by David Anderson, 1989 January 5; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 4, Cassette 5)
    Interview is closed due to a lack of a signed release by Bates.
  - David S. Brown interviewed by David Anderson, 1989 July 17; 4 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 6, Cassette 7, Cassette 8, Cassette 9)
    Interview is closed due to lack of signed release from Brown.
  - David S. Brown interviewed by David Anderson, 1989 August 3; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 10, Cassette 11)
  - David S. Brown interview, 1989 October 3; 2 Cassettes (Box 5, Cassette 12, Cassette 13)
    Interview is closed due to a lack of a signed release from Brown.
  - Francis Willis Brown interviewed by David Anderson with Ed McKee from the Department of Athletics, 1991 January 11; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 14)
    A signed release by Brown was not completed. The interview can be made avaialble onsite and/or for research purposes, but coyright would need to be determined for further use.
    This is stored on one cassette tape and would need to be digitized.
    Biographical / Historical
    George Washington University class of 1924, GW Law School class of 1926.
  - Elizabeth Burtner interviewed By Lee S. Bielski, 1989 August 24; 2 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 16, Box 5, Cassette 16)
    Burtner taught modern dance at George Washington University from 1937 through the early 1970s
  - Charles Diehl interviewed by David Anderson, 1990 January 29; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Cassette 19, Box R2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Diehl
  - GW President Lloyd Elliot interviews upon retirement, 1987 (Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24)
    These interviews exist as original and duplicate cassette tapes, printed transcripts, and 3.5" floppy disks apparently containing the transcript files. The disks are stored with the cassette tapes.
  - Roderick S. French interviewed by Ashley Locke, 2011 August 4-17; 4 digital object(s)
    Dr. Roderick S. French served The George Washington University for twenty-eight years as a faculty member and administrator.
    Dr. French earned an A.B. in philosophy from Kenyon College, an M.Div. in church history, theology and biblical studies from the Episcopal Theological School in Cambridge, Massachusetts, an S.T.M. in Modern church history from Union Theological Seminary in New York City, and a Ph.D. in American Civilization from The George Washington University. French began his career as the Executive Director of the Youth Department of the World Council of Churches in Geneva (1959-64). He later served as Special Assistant to the Director of the Office of Public Affairs of the Peace Corps from 1967 to 1968.
    Dr. French joined The George Washington University as a Ph.D. student in 1968 and was appointed as the Associate Director of the University's Division of Experimental Programs in 1969. He was made director of the Division in 1979, and was responsible for university-wide curricular innovation and academic program development. In 1984 he was made Vice President for Academic Affairs, a position he held until 1995 when he stepped down to work with the University Honors Program. Dr. French left GW in 1997 to become the First Chancellor of the American University of Sharjah in the United Arab Emirates. Today, he is Chancellor Emeritus of the American University of Sharjah, a member of its Board of Trustees, and secretary of the Board of Directors of the AUS-USA Foundation.
    This oral history interview was conducted on August 3, 12, and 17, 2011 by Assistant University Archivist, Ashley Locke. Total running time: 4 hours and 27 minutes. The interview includes the following subjects:
    1) French's work for the World Council of Churches in Geneva. 2) French's work for the Peace Corps Headquarters 3) The socio-political atmosphere of Washington, D.C. and the country in the summer of 1968 4) George Washington University's campus culture in the late 1960s 5) GW President Lloyd Elliott 6) The Division of Experimental Programs 7) National Endowment for the Humanities Challenge Grant 8) Environmental Studies 9) Pedagogy at GW in the 1970s, educational reform and innovations 10)DEP Staff: Perry Wallace Sirulnik Seldman Lear Love Aron 11) The Free and Easy Society 12) The Dilthey Society 13) D.C. Community Humanities Council 14) National Trust for Historic Preservation 15) French's service as the Vice President for Academic Affairs 16) Council of Deans 17) Reorganization of School of International Affairs 18) Diversification of Student Body and Faculty, Educational Opportunities Program 19) Research 20) Enrollment Management 21) Radio and TV at GW 22) Naval ROTC unit at GW 23) Gelman Library 24) Middle States Accreditation 25) Continuing Education 26) Virginia Science and Technology Campus 27) GW Board of Trustees in the 1980s 28) The Center for Washington Area Studies 29) University seminar
  - Frederick Gutheim interviewed by Karen Wickre, 1977 April 19; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 4, Cassette 1)
    Interview closed due to lack of release from Gutheim.
    Background in historic preservation and development of the Graduate Program in Historic Preservation at George Washington University by the program's director
  - Hatchet alumni interviewed by David Anderson, 2004 March; 1 folder(s) (Box R2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of releases signed by participants.
    Melven Bers ('41), Paul Welch ('57 law), Greg Valliere ('74), Deborah Solomon ('94), Dave Mann ('99), and Andrew Novak ('05) interviewed as a group about their experiences working for the Hatchet.
  - Thelma Hunt interviewed by David Anderson, 1989 May 12; 3 Cassettes 3 copies of 1 cassette each; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 31, Cassette 32, Cassette 33)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Hunt.
  - Thelma Hunt interviewed by David Anderson, 1990 February 18; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 34)
  - Douglas Johnson interviewed by Tasha Dorsey, 2014 April 11; 1 digital object(s)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Douglas Johnson was born on August 3, 1955 in Clyo, Georgia to Bennit and Victoria Johnson. He is married to Bessie Louise Johnson, and has two children, Vicki Valorie Johnson and Douglas Johnson, Jr. He was educated at Effingham County High School in Springfield, Georgia and is a veteran of the Vietnam war.
    The oral history discusses Douglas Johnson's career working at GW in food services and his life experiences.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Susan R. Ratnoff, 1974 February 19 and April 2; 1 Reels (Box R2, Box 1, Reel 17)
    Excerpts from interview appear in a student paper titled "The History Department During the Marvin Era (1927-1959)," which is filed under Merriman.
    Interview is closed due to a lack of a signed release from Kayser.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Steven M. Raser, 1974 April 3; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 5, Cassette 35)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Kayser.
    Topic of the interview was the history of the university bookstore
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 March 10; 3 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 1, Box 4, Cassette 2, Cassette 3, Cassette 4, Box 1, Reel 18)
    Kayser's family background and childhood: recollections of Georgetown at the turn of the 20th century
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 April 4; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s); 1 Reels (Box 18, Folder 2, Box 4, Cassette 5, Box 1, Reel 19, Side 1)
    Recollections of Washington
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 April 14; 2 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 3, Box 4, Cassette 6, Cassette 7, Box 1, Reel 19, Side 2)
    University life at George Washington University, 1914-1917
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 April 22; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 4, Box 4, Cassette 8, Box 1, Reel 20, Side 1)
    Kayser's first professional years at the university, 1917-1921.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 April 28-29; 2 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 5, Box 4, Cassette 9, Cassette 10, Box 1, Reel 20)
    The 1910 crisis at George Washington University
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 May 19; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 6, Box 4, Cassette 11, Box 1, Reel 21)
    George Washington University in the early 1920s
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 June 2; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 7, Box 4, Cassette 12, Box 1, Reel 21)
    Personal activities at George Washington University in the 1920s
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Steven M. Raser, 1975 June 27; 1 Cassettes (Box 5, Cassette 36)
    Interview is closed due to a lack of signed release from Kayser.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 August 25; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 8, Box 4, Cassette 13, Box 1, Reel 22, Side 2)
    Years of transition: University development in the 1930s
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 August 26; 1 Cassettes; 2 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 9, Box 4, Cassette 14, Box 1, Reel 22, Side 2, Reel 23, Side 23)
    Organization of Summer Sessions
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 September 9 and October 21; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s); 1 Reels (Box 18, Folder 10, Box 4, Cassette 15, Cassette 16, Box 1, Reel 23)
    Organization of the Division of University Students
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1975 December 16; 1 Reels; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 11, Box 4, Cassette 17, Box 1, Reel 23)
    American Historical Association
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 March 5, 9, and 29; 3 Cassettes; 2 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 1, Box 4, Cassette 18, Cassette 19, Cassette 20, Box 1, Reel 23, Reel 24)
    Physical growthh and development of the George Washington University physcial campus to 1930
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 April 6; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s); 1 Reels (Box 19, Folder 2, Box 4, Cassette 21, Box 1, Reel 24)
    The physical growth and development of the George Washington University campus in the early Marvin years
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Linda Beattie, 1976 November 29; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 3, Box 4, Cassette 22, Box 1, Reel 24)
    The history and practices of Fraternities and Sorrorities at George Washington University
  - Elmer Kayser interviewed by unknown person about "GW Campus: Past and Present", 1977; 5 Cassettes (Box 6, Cassette 1, Cassette 2, Cassette 3, Cassette 4, Cassette 5)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Kayser.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Linda Beattie, 1977 January 24; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 4, Box 9, Cassette 23, Box 1, Reel 25, Side 1)
    Alfred F.W. Schmidt, university librarian
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Linda Beattie, 1977 January 31 and February 2; 2 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 5, Box 4, Cassette 24, Cassette 25, Box 1, Reel 25)
    Character sketches of George Washington University faculty
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering with Jack Wilson, 1977 May 13; 2 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 19, Folder 6, Box 4, Cassette 26, Cassette 27, Box 1, Reel 26)
    Walking tour of Georgetown
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1977 May 23; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s); 1 Reels (Box 19, Folder 7, Box 4, Cassette 28, Cassette 29, Box 1, Reel 26)
    Kayser's research before writing the university history, Bricks Without Straw.
  - Elmer Louis Kayser interview, 1981 April 21; Series 1 Subseries 1; 4 Reels (Box 1, Reel 27, Reel 28, Reel 29, Reel 30)
    Interview is closed because of lack of a release signed by Kayser.
  - Donald R. Lehman interviewed by Ashley Locke, 2011 May 3 - 10; 4 digital object(s)
    Dr. Donald R. Lehman (1940-) retired from The George Washington University on 31 December 2010 after serving more than thirty-eight years as a faculty member and administrator.
    Dr. Lehman earned a BA in Physics from Rutgers University in 1962, an MS in Space Physics from the Air Force Institute of Technology in 1964, and a Ph.D. in Theoretical Physics from The George Washington University in 1970. Lehman joined the GW faculty as an Assistant Professor of Physics in 1972, becoming a fully Professor in 1982. He was made Chair of the Department of Physics in 1987, and he founded the Center for Nuclear Studies at the University in 1990.
    From 1993 to 1996, Dr. Lehman held the position of Associate Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies. He was appointed Vice President for Academic Affairs in 1996, and served in this role until 2002 when he was made the George Gamow Professor of Theoretical Physics. He was the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs from 2003 to 2010, and in 2010 he served as Senior Advisor to the President until his retirement.
    This oral history interview was conducted on May 3, 5, and 10, 2011 by Assistant University Archivist, Ashley Locke. Total running time: 3 hours and 35 minutes. The interview includes the following subjects:
    -Dr. Lehman's experiences as a student and instructor at The George Washington University -President Stephen J. Trachtenberg -President Steven Knapp -GW's Center for Nuclear Studies -The Virginia Science and Technology Campus -The George Washington University's absorption of Mount Vernon College -The Washington Research Library Consortium -The Southeastern Universities Research Association -The University's Writing Program -The 2003 Strategic Plan for Academic Excellence -Tenure-promotion culture at GW -Columbian College of Arts and Sciences Dean Peg Barratt -Elliott School of International Affairs Dean Michael Brown -School of Business and Public Management Dean Susan Phillips -School of Business and Public Management Dean Doug Guthrie -Law School Dean Frederick M. Lawrence -Law School Dean Paul Schiff Berman -School of Engineering and Applied Science Dean David S. Dolling -Graduate School of Education and Human Development Dean Mary Hatwood Futrell -Graduate School of Education and Human Development Dean Michael J. Feuer -College of Professional Studies Dean Kathleen Burke. -School of Public Health and Health Services Dean Lynn Goldman -The creation of the College of Professional Studies. -The reorganization of the Graduate School of Education and Human Development in 2007 -The reorganization of the School of Engineering and Applied Science -Technology transfer -The creation of the University Roundtable -The George Washington Institute of Public Policy
  - Joseph Litwins interviewed by G. David Anderson, 1992 February 5; 3 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 9, Cassette 10, Cassette 11)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Litwins.
  - John Madden interviewed by G. David Anderson, 1992 Febrary 5; 3 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 12, Cassette 13, Cassette 14)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Madden.
  - John Russell Mason interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 June 7; 1 Cassettes; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 4, Cassette 30, Box 1, Reel 16)
    Reminiscences of the former University Librarian, 1933-1966; also memories of student life at George Washington University in 1918
  - John Russell Mason interviewed by Elmer Louis Kayser, 1976 June 11; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s); 2 Cassettes (Box R2, Box 1, Reel 16, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)
    Interview is closed at Mason's instructions.
    Kayser and Mason discuss their decades at George Washington University, including fairly candid discussions of Cloyd Heck Marvin and others
  - Howard R. Merriman interviewed by Susan R. Ratnoff, 1974 March 14; 1 folder(s) (Box R2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of release signed by Merriman.
    Merriman's reminiscences of his years in the History Department at George Washington University. Interview is an appendix to a student paper titled "The History Department During the Marvin Era (1927-1959)," which also includes excerpts from interviews with Elmer Louis Kayser and Prof. Wood Gray.
  - Howard Merriman interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1977 June 27 and 28; 1 Reels; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 1, Reel 14, Box 4, Cassette 31, Cassette 32)
    Discussion of the organization of the George Washington University Faculty Senate by the Professor of History Emeritus.
  - Frank N. Miller, Jr. interviewed by David Anderson, 1996 April 3; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 17, Cassette 18)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a signed release from Miller.
  - Charles Naeser interviewed by G. David Anderson, 1996 October 23; 2 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 6, Cassette 19, Cassette 20)
  - George Nordlinger interviewed by David Anderson, 1991-04-22; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 21)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Nordlinger.
  - Ruth Osborn interviewed by David Anderson, 2007 May 7; 1 folder(s) (Box R2)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Osborn.
  - Martha J. Ross interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1974 February 13; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 4, Cassette 33)
    Development of personal interest in oral history; origins of oral history workshop at George Washington University and how workshop was conducted; comments on the oral history movement and individuals prominent within it; transfer to University of Maryland and establishment of oral history class there
  - Alice Sheftel interviewed by Mary Jo Deering, 1976 September 20; 1 Reels; 1 folder(s); 1 Cassettes (Box 16, Box 17, Reel 12, Box 7, Cassette 32)
    Alice Sheftel, Associate University Librarian, reminisces on her long career with the university library.
  - Dallas Shirley interviewed by Lee BIelski, 1989 August 23; 1 folder(s); 3 Cassettes (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 22, Cassette 23, Cassette 24)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Shirley.
  - Harvey Snyder interviewed by David Anderson, 2006 May 26 and June 6; 2 folder(s) (Box 16)
  - Henry Solomon interviewed by David Anderson, 2006 August 9 - September 29; 5 Cassettes; 5 folder(s) (Box 16, Box 7, Cassette 24, Cassette 25, Cassette 26, Cassette 27, Cassette 30)
    Consists of a series of five interviews conducted on August 9, 16, 23 and 30, and Setpember 29, 2006.
  - Murray Stein interviewed by David Anderson, 1997 July 21; 1 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 31)
    Interview is closed due to lack of a release signed by Stein.
  - Bernard Svedlow and Gerry Svedlow interviewed by David Anderson, 1991 October 4; 5 Cassettes; 1 folder(s) (Box R2, Box 6, Cassette 33, Cassette 34, Cassette 35, Box 7, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)